Hello and welcome back to
another video with ItsDrDan.
And today we're going to be learning
about how to classify aldoses and
ketoses, what you will, which is
something that you're going to
find in introductory biochemistry.
So with these, these are carbohydrates
that have aldehyde and ketone groups.
So whenever we are seeing an aldose,
so for the first example, all the way
up top, You can see that we have the
aldehyde, which is all the way on carbon
number one for the first structure.
So let's just write this one down here.
And then for the, uh, ketone, we can
see that on carbon Number two, we always
have our ketone with biomolecules.
So we're going to go through step
by step how we can actually classify
these as aldoses, ketoses, what exactly
are they, and how we can count the
number of carbons in these different
structures and how we can label
them for your biochemistry course.
Let's take a look at it.
All right, so the first thing is when
we are classifying carbohydrates,
these are known as simple sugars.
because these are
specifically monosaccharides.
So whenever we have a monosaccharide,
that means there is one single
carbohydrate that we are showing.
Now with most of these
different carbohydrates,
they have the ending of ose.
So whenever we see that ose ending,
that's telling you, hey, this is a
sugar, this is a carbohydrate, um,
being that it has the carbon chain,
it has that aldehyde or ketone.
And it has those alternating OHs that
we will see in Fischer projections or
Hayworth projections to illustrate these.
Let's take a look even farther into this.
So when we are given a carbohydrate
or a simple monosaccharide, the
first step is that you have to
identify the functional group.
which is what you're going to, what you
will receive training on how to do from
an, from your introductory organic class.
So with this, what you're looking
for is two major functional groups.
These are aldehydes and ketones.
So when we have our first one, so with our
aldehyde, what's going to happen is we're
going to take that ALD portion and put
the ose ending on it to make it an aldose.
With ketose or ketone, we take ketone
and then we transport that into ketose.
Now, the reason why I highlighted these
specific portions of the biochem is that
when you actually classify these, you're
going to use the aldo or keto to help
explain exactly what kind of carbohydrate
or simple sugar you are looking at.
And always remember the aldehyde or the
aldose is always going to be on carbon
number one and the ketose will always be
on carbon number two for simple sugars.
Let's go to step number two.
Step two, now that we identified
what functional group we have.
We're now going to count
the number of carbons.
So there are generally most of these
simple carbohydrates go up to typically
seven carbons most of the time.
So if we have, let's say three
carbons, this is going to be a
trios, so, or trios, so think of
the triangle, a triangle, so trios.
Now, when we have four, this is a
tetros, five is pentos, six is hexos.
So for the next portion, we are
going to combine step one and two,
which being that we have the aldehyde
and ketone from the first step.
So we're going to take aldo or keto,
depending on the functional group,
and we're going to combine that with
the number of carbons that we have.
So if I have, let's say, the example here,
what you're going to do is we're going to
first do is identify the functional group
and what we can see up here is that, oh,
well, we have an aldo or an aldehyde.
Okay.
So that would be the first portion here.
So let's write aldehyde is what we have.
Uh, as our functional group.
So it's gonna be Aldo.
Now how many carbons does it have?
So what we will do is we
are going to number, right?
We have 1, 2, 3.
We start numbering all the way at
the top of our Fisher projection.
We number down.
So start all the way as close to
the most oxidized carbon as you
can to the aldehyde or the ketone.
So now that we have three carbons,
this is going to be an Aldo trios.
as our classification for this structure.
Okay, so that is all you have to do
is when you are classifying them.
Let's go through a couple
different examples and practice
these different skills.
Let's take a look.
So with the following questions,
we're going to classify the
following carbohydrates.
So we're going to go
through our steps, right?
Step one plus two.
putting our two things together.
So the very first step is that we
need to count and classify how many,
classify what our functional group is.
So on the structure on the left
we can see that oh we have an
aldehyde, right, because we are
looking right here on carbon number
one we see that C double bond O.
So that means that this will be an aldo.
Now, how many carbons do we have?
Well, we're going to go down our chain.
We see we have one, two, three, four,
five, six carbons on our structure.
So now what is that going to be?
Well, in this case, it's going to be
an aldo hexose for our title, right?
So we can see we have hex for six.
So it's going to be aldo hexose.
So and that will be how we would
classify the structure on the left.
Now what about the structure above?
Well same idea, we gotta first
identify what the functional group is.
And when we go through numbering here,
right, one, two, three, four, five, we can
see that on carbon number two we have our
carbonyl, right, so our C double bond O.
So what that means is when we
have that there we have a keto.
And being that there's five carbons,
that's going to be ketopentose, is
going to be the name for that structure.
Okay, or sorry, not name, it's going to
be the classification for that structure.
Let's take a look at another exam,
another two examples and keep
practicing it for our last two.
So if this is something that you want
to practice, pause the video, see if
you can do it on yourself for yourself
before I go through the example.
So we're going to start by class.
So number our carbon.
So we got one, two, three, four,
and we see that on our carbon
number two, we have a carbonyl.
So that's C double bondo that tells
you, Hey, we have a keto, right?
Or ketone.
So it's going to be keto and
being that we have four of them.
This is going to be Ketotetros
for our classification.
We're going to do the same
thing on the next one, right?
One, two, three, four, five.
And what we see is, oh, there's a
C double bond O all the way up top.
So this is going to be aldo and
tos, being that there are five.
And that would be how
you classify this one.
I hope that this video helped.
It's a little short one just
to go through the basics of
how to classify carbohydrates.
Look for my follow up videos on
how to draw Hayworth, uh, Hayworth
projections, Fischer projections, and
more to come with introductory biochem.
If this video helped you, hit
that like, subscribe button,
help support the channel.
It keeps growing, and thank you so much
for watching, and I appreciate you.
Have a wonderful day.
I'll see you all later.
Bye now.